it's no secret that magic the Gathering
can be a complicated game at times and
with its 281-page rulebook it's tough to
remember all of the different
interactions but here is one slightly
Advanced rule I'm going to break down
for you as it can not only help you win
games it can also stop you from losing
them too and this isn't just for
Commander this is for all formats of
magic
so let's talk about appnap otherwise
known as active player non-active player
going into this video all you need to
know is a basic understanding of the
stack and triggered abilities
here's a super quick refresher just to
make sure we're all on the same page
the stack is the Zone in which spells
activated abilities and triggered
abilities wait to resolve first in last
out
triggered abilities begin with the words
when whenever or act
for example she aldrid the apocalypse
says whenever you draw a card you gain
to life and whenever an opponent draws a
card they lose to life
these are not to be confused with
activated abilities
activated abilities always have a cost
such as paying Mana or tapping a
creature followed by a colon and then
the result of paying set cost
here's a quick test for you
I'm in a two-player game it's my turn
and we're currently in my second main
phase
my opponent and I are both on one life
they have a shielded the Apocalypse in
play and I have underworld of dreams we
both have no cards in hand
I pass the turn to my opponent they draw
a swamp for their turn
do they survive
feel free to pause the video and think
about this
three two one
the answer is no they will go to zero
life before they get a chance to gain
life from their children
but why is that
this is all thanks to appnap active
player non-active player
so let's break this down
firstly who is the active player
the active player is whoever's turn it
currently is and the non-active player
or players are everybody else
when multiple triggered abilities
trigger at the same time
whoever the active player is puts all
abilities they control on the stack
first in whichever order they like
then the non-active player puts all the
abilities they control on the stack on
top of the current abilities on the
stack
also they place them in whichever order
they like
if there are more than two players in a
game you would repeat this process in
turn order for each player who controls
a triggered ability waiting to go on the
stack
and as we know with the stack first in
last out so whoever the last non-active
player was their abilities will resolve
first and the active players abilities
while they'll resolve last
so let's go back to that previous
example
my opponent draws their card for the
turn
two triggered abilities trigger my
opponent being the active player in this
situation puts their Shield Reds game
two life ability on the stack and
because I'm the non-active player I then
put my underworld of Dreams ability on
the stack
once we resolve the stack my ability
resolves first putting my opponent to
zero life and then thanks to state-based
checks my opponent loses the game for
being on zero life
so the next time you see multiple
triggered abilities at the same time
just remember appnap
active player non-active player
if you learned something in this video
today feel free to hit that like button
if there's something you didn't
understand or you need a hand with
another rules question let me know down
in the comments below
if you want to check out another rules
video how about this one here
it's all about the new token rules that
came into effect with the launch of
March of the machines
I hope you enjoy it thank you so much
for watching and I'll see you guys next
time